Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is סנהדרין נ"ה Sanhedrin
nun hei Sanhedrin 55 we pick up on סנהדרין נ"ד ע"ב Sanhedrin
nun dalet amud bet 54B six lines from the bottom four lines
before the end of the line תנו רבנן. Tanur rabanan. Okay and
we are in the middle of the various sexual sins. תנו רבנן.
Tanur rabanan. זכור Zachor when you are dealing with male on male
intercourse and זכור zachor again points out that with the ו vav
it refers to the man being penetrated. So לא עשו בו קטן
כגדול lo asu bo katan kegadol it is not always the same
a minor and an adult. So this means that in the case
of male on male intercourse you need as we know in a
case well let's start first with heterosexual intercourse which is the עריות
arayot then as long it's only one of the it's possible for
one of the parties to be an adult and for that party
to be חייב chayav you don't need both parties to be the
adult but you need the other party to be considered to be
participating in the act of intercourse. We're not going to deal now
of course with the issue about child abuse and sexual abuse and
all of that but it has to be an age in which
it is considered an act of sexual intercourse. And if that's true
for the minor then that would be defined as an act of
sexual intercourse that the adult then would get the appropriate punishment. So
if it is a case let's say of heterosexual then it is
a if it's a minor man he have to be nine years
and a day old to be having intercourse with a woman in
a case of עריות arayot for the woman to be liable. Only
then is it considered an act of intercourse. If it is a
case of an adult male and a minor female then the female
would have to be three years and a day old for to
be considered an act of intercourse. Less than that is not considered
an act of intercourse. Okay that has to do with חז"ל'ס Chazal's
assumption about whether the hymen would grow back less than three or
in the case of a man being nine in terms of it
being like soon to be an act of getting an erection and
being considered a real act of intercourse. Okay so those are the
basic parameters. Now how about male on male? What would be the
הלכה halacha for the one being penetrated? If it was an adult
who was the man doing the being penetrated then the man who
was doing the penetrating would have to be nine years and a
day. That we know for to be considered an act of intercourse
for the man who is penetrating in any context of intercourse nine
years and a day. But if it is the man penetrating is
an adult what would have to be the minor age of the
one being penetrated? Okay that is that is the question here.
So minors are not like adults there's a difference. But where to
draw the line is not clear. בהמה עשו בה קטנה כגדולה Behema
asu bah ktana kegdola and in a case of bestiality it does
not matter the age of the animal obviously. Okay מאי לא עשו
בו קטן כגדול? mai lo asu bo katan kegadol? אמר רב לא
עשו ביאת פחות מבן תשע שנים כבן תשע שנים Amar Rav lo
asu biat pachat miben tesha shanim keben tesha shanim that the line
is nine years. Nine years and a day is different than under
nine years. You go by a definition since he's also a man
you go by when he would be considered to do an act
of intercourse which would be when he would be nine years and
a day even though in this case he is the one being
penetrated. And רש"י Rashi says that this is also linked to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who learned out the prohibition of the נשכב nishkav
from the שוכב. shochev. ושמואל אמר לא עשו ביאת פחות מבן שלוש
שנים כבן שלוש שנים. Ushmuel amar lo asu biat pachat miben shalosh
shanim keben shalosh shanim. And שמואל Shmuel says no it's a difference
of three years and a day versus less than three years. במאי
קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? What's the difference what are they debating about? רב
סבר כל דאיתא בשוכב איתא בנשכב וכל דליתא בשוכב ליתא בנשכב Rav
savar kol d'ita b'shochev ita b'nishkav v'kol d'leita b'shochev leita b'nishkav that
the שוכב shochev and the נשכב nishkav are linked. So if a
man can be of the age where he is considered to be
the שוכב shochev the penetrator nine years and a day which would
make the other man who is an adult liable so then also
that is the definition of him being participating in the sexual act
even as the נשכב. nishkav. But if he is not of the
age of being a שוכב shochev then he cannot also be considered
to be a sexual act being a נשכב. nishkav. ושמואל סבר משכבי
אשה כתיב Ushmuel savar mishkivei ishah ketiv
no in this case the one who is the man being penetrated
it is defined by the תורה Torah as the sleeping of a
woman so he is sort of seen in this sort of woman
role here and therefore since a woman the age is three years
and a day for the man it is also three years and
a day. תניא כוותיה דרב Tanya kavatei d'Rav we taught like רב
Rav זכר בן תשע שנים ויום אחד. zachar ben tesha shanim v'yom
echad. When it comes to the prohibition of male on male intercourse
it is nine years and a day. And רש"י Rashi says this
has to be talking about the case of the נשכב nishkav because
from the perspective of the שוכב shochev we always know that when
it comes to the man doing the penetrating we go by nine
years and a day. So since the ברייתא braita here specifically identify
male on male intercourse and saying nine years and a day it
is telling you specifically that that is the same
age used for the נשכב nishkav as well. Now the ברייתא braita
continues הבא על בהמה haba al behema that's different with different definitions
of different categories. In a case of bestiality, בין כדרכה בין שלא
כדרכה, bein kedarka bein shelo kedarka, whether it is if a man
is penetrating a female animal, cow, whether it is vaginal or anal,
does not matter. ואישה המביאה בהמה עליה, v'ishah ha-meviah behemah aleha, and
if a woman is being penetrated by an animal, by a male
animal, בין כדרכה בין שלא כדרכה, bein kedarka bein shelo kedarka, whether
it is penetrating her vaginally or anally, חייב. chayav. Okay, so that
is all those particulars. Now, just three lines from the top, עמוד
א. amud aleph. דרש רב נחמן בר רב חסדא. darash Rav Nachman
bar Rav Chisda. רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda explicated, באישה שני משכבות ובבהמה משכב אחד. be'ishah shnei mishkavot u'vevehemah
mishkav echad.
By a woman, there are two משכבות, mishkavot, משכבי אישה, mishkevei ishah,
which is vaginal or anal, but by an animal, it is only
one, okay, because it doesn't say משכבי mishkevei by an animal. So
what does that mean?
So that's basically arguing on this ברייתא braita and it is saying
that when a woman brings an animal on her, is penetrated by
an animal, it's whether it's vaginal or anal because that's משכבי אישה,
mishkevei ishah, but when an animal is being penetrated, it would only
be vaginal, okay, it seems to be. One wonders if a man
is penetrating a male animal, what would you say in that case?
But okay. מתקיף לה רב פפא. matkif lah Rav Pappa. רב פפא
Rav Pappa challenged, אדרבה, aderaba, you could say the exact opposite. אישה
דאורחה היא, ishah de'orchah hi, משכב מחייב, mishkav mechayev, אמידה אחרינא לא
מחייב. amida achrina lo mechayev.
You know, by the case of a woman where we normally expect,
you know, whatever, intercourse is a natural thing, you could say maybe
the Torah should only be מחייב mechayev vaginal intercourse, which is the
sort of natural form of intercourse, and not anal intercourse, אמידה אחרינא
לא מחייב. amida achrina lo mechayev. בבהמה דלאו אורחה היא, bevehemah delav
orchah hi, but when you,
maybe, you know, when an animal, when it's a case of an
animal penetrating a woman, maybe you know that's only vaginal, but when
it's a case of an animal דלאו אורחה היא, delav orchah hi,
לחייב עליה כל נקב ונקב. lechayev aleha kol nekev ve-nekev. You know,
since that's not actually normally considered intercourse, right, with an animal, then,
you know, what difference does it make which orifice it is? You
know, it's not a normal act of intercourse, so if the Torah
is telling you that it's forbidden, maybe it should not matter which
orifice it is. Now, that's a little funny because it's also not
a normal act of intercourse for a male animal to penetrate a
woman, but anyway, he is just challenging this idea that even though
it doesn't say משכבי mishkevei by the animal, but since that's not
a normal intercourse about a man penetrating an animal, why should it
matter at all, and why should you even need it to say
משכבי? mishkevei? Okay, so תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
or some of the גרסא girsa is תניא דלא כוותייהו, tanya d'lo
kevatveihu, we taught like neither of them: זכר בן תשע שנים ויום
אחד, zachar bein tesha shanim ve-yom echad, period.
When it comes to a male being penetrated, nine years and a
day. הבא בבהמה בין כדרכה בין שלא כדרכה ואישה המביאה בהמה עליה
בין כדרכה בין שלא כדרכה, haba b'behemah bein kedarka bein shelo kedarka
v'ishah ha-meviah behemah aleha bein kedarka bein shelo kedarka, חייב. chayav. So
we do not distinguish, we do not say
in either case of bestiality, whether
it's a man on an animal or an animal on a woman,
we say that they are both go, whether כדרכה, kedarka, whether שלא
כדרכה. shelo kedarka. Okay, so that is what the ברייתא braita says
against making a distinction one direction or the other.
Okay, חייב. chayav. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא. amar lei Ravina le-Rava. So
we are now beyond that. Said רבינא Ravina to רבא, Rava, המערה
בזכר מהו? ha-me'areh be-zachar mahu? What happens when it is only initial
penetration? So there, מערה me'areh is what you are חייב, chayav, the
definition of intercourse in a heterosexual context is when the tip of
the penis enters into the vagina. Okay, that's called מערה. me'areh. There's
a prior stage which is called נשיקה, neshikah, which is when the,
you know, the penis touches the vagina but doesn't enter in, and
then there's גמר ביאה gmar biah which is when the entire shaft
enters in, but מערה me'areh is when the tip enters in and
that's already considered to be an act of intercourse. Okay, some actually
say that even נשיקה neshikah is that, but we assume that no,
that מערה me'areh is even נשיקה, neshikah, even touching, but no, we
say it's only when it enters in. So what happens, that's when
you're talking about
heterosexual, okay, it's even in the case of anal intercourse but in
a heterosexual context. What happens if it's a case
of about a man on man? So in that case, המערה בזכר
מהו? ha-me'areh be-zachar mahu? So the גמרא gemara says, המערה בזכר, ha-me'areh
be-zachar, what are you talking about? משכבי אישה כתיב בה. mishkevei ishah
ktiv bah. It says the sleepings of a woman. So since we
learn out from that prohibition that it's defined as it would be
intercourse with a woman and therefore, you know, anal intercourse by woman
is also whether anal or vaginal is defined by מערה me'areh is
the definition of intercourse, that applies by the man as well. Okay,
so because משכבי אישה mishkevei ishah tells us. Now what's interesting though
is that the גמרא gemara does not say that, you know, we
just normally apply the same definition of intercourse as we apply by
all the עריות. arayot. That we learn out because all the עריות
arayot are linked to one another and
since... And we cannot assume that something that applies to the עריות
arayot applies to male on male except that we do have a
פסוק pasuk משכבי אשה mishkeve isha that specifically defines the act of
intercourse the same way, but in general we would not necessarily categorize
it with all the other עריות arayot and that's an interesting sort
of conceptual point. Okay, so fine, but the גמרא Gemara concedes that
because it says משכבי אשה mishkeve isha it's going to be defined
the same way.
אלא, Ela, המערה בבהמה hame'areh bevehema מהו? mahu? What if this was
a case about intercourse with an animal, you know, would it be
defined just as the beginning, the tip enters in? אמר ליה, Amar
leh, אם אינו
ענין, im eino inyan, אמר ליה, amar leh, אם אינו ענין להערה
דכתיב גבי אחות אביו ואחות אמו
im eino inyan leha'arah
dechetiv gavei achot aviv ve'achot imo, דלא צריכא. delo tzricha. Now because
the פסוק pasuk in a few פסוקים psukim it says את מקורה
הערה, et mekora he'erah, he uncovered her source. Okay, and that word
הערה he'erah is where we learn this idea of מערה, me'areh, even
just beginning of penetration. Now it says it in two places. It
says it about a sister of a father or mother, an aunt,
and it also says it about a case of נדה. niddah. From
the נדה niddah case we learn that all the עריות arayot are
linked and we apply it to all the עריות arayot that definition
of intercourse. So why did the תורה Torah have to then say
it again by the case of the aunt? So that's what we're
going to say is תנהו ענין tneh'u inyan that it applies even
to this unusual case, the case of an animal.
Okay, so let's read that again. אם אינו ענין להערה im eino
inyan leha'arah דכתיב dechetiv גבי gavei אחות אביו achot aviv ואחות אמו,
ve'achot imo if it's not needed to tell you the definition of
מערה me'areh when it speaks by the case of the aunt, דלא
צריכא delo tzricha that's not needed, דהקיש להערה דנדה, dehikeish leha'arah deniddah,
that's linked to the case of מערה me'areh that it says by
נדה. niddah. So by נדה niddah so therefore and all of the
עריות arayot are linked to one another. So therefore since it said
again this word הערה he'erah by aunt, תנהו ענין להערה דבבהמה, tneh'u
inyan leha'arah debevehema, it's extra so use it to apply you to
the case, to apply it to a case where we wouldn't necessarily
have applied it, where things aren't linked and where you don't have
משכבי אשה mishkeve isha like it says by the case of males,
and you just and therefore we're going to apply it to the
case of animals. So the גמרא Gemara says מכדי michdi בהמה behema
מחייבי מיתות בית דין היא, mechayvei mitot beit din hi, למה לי
דכתיב הערה דידה lama li dechetiv he'arah didah גבי חייבי כריתות? gavei
chayvei keritot? So now the גמרא Gemara says okay, but it's still
like a big jump to go from the heterosexual context of aunt
to apply it to בהמה behema and say oh it's extra we
can apply it. בהמה Behema is a case of מחייבי מיתה. mechayvei
mitah. The case of aunt is a case of חייבי כריתות. chayvei
keritot. לכתביה גבי חייבי מיתות בית דין וליגמר חייבי מיתות בית דין
מחייבי מיתות בית דין, lichtveih gavei chayvei mitot beit din veligmar chayvei
mitot beit din mechayvei mitot beit din, הואיל וכולי קרא לדרשה הוא
דאתא. ho'il vechulei kra ledrasha hu de'ata.
Oh I'm sorry that's already the answer. לכתביה גבי חייבי מיתות בית
דין. Lichtveih gavei chayvei mitot beit din. Why did the תורה Torah
not, if it wanted to use this extra word of הערה he'erah
to teach me בהמה, behema, why didn't it place it in a
case of one of the עריות arayot that's at least a little
more similar to בהמה, behema, like one that's מחייבי מיתות בית דין?
mechayvei mitot beit din? So the גמרא's Gemara answer is no, הואיל
וכולי קרא לדרשה הוא דאתא כתיבא נמי מילתא דדרשה. ho'il vechulei kra
ledrasha hu de'ata ctiva nami milta dedrasha. No, because the whole פסוק
pasuk by
אחות אם achot em and אחות אב achot av is all like
extra. We're going to see later,
excuse me not later but in יבמות, Yevamot, that anyway there's a
that you know everything is sort of repeated in אחרי מות Acharei
Mot and in קדושים, Kedoshim, in אחרי מות Acharei Mot it's the
prohibition and in קדושים Kedoshim it's the punishment. So the גמרא Gemara
and particularly by אחות אם achot em and אחות אב achot av
the גמרא's Gemara going to say that this whole פסוק pasuk is
extra and you דורש doresh a lot of things by it. So
since there's a lot of things that you know the תורה Torah
is sort of throwing in there to דורש, doresh, it also puts
in this idea of הערה he'erah by בהמה. behema. So you're right,
if it was only one extra word and we had to figure
out where to put it the תורה Torah should have put it
in a case of מחייבי מיתות בית דין mechayvei mitot beit din
to learn out to apply בבהמה. bevehema. It doesn't even explain why
it doesn't say it directly by בהמה, behema, but okay. It should
have put it in some place that was more comparable. But since
the whole thing is packed full of דרשות, drashot, extra דרשות drashot
from this פסוק pasuk by אחות אם achot em and אחות אב,
achot av, let's also have this included as well. But that at
least is the resolution that the definition of of intercourse is the
same by זכר zachar and by בהמה behema as it is by
the heterosexual context. Okay, בעי מיניה רב אחדיבוי בר אמי מרב ששת,
Ba'ei minei Rav Achdivoi bar Ami meRav Sheshet, המערה בעצמו מהו? hame'areh
be'atzmo mahu? This is a pretty just whatever
bizarre and disturbing case. The גמרא Gemara says let's say a man
has
a very long penis and able to bend it and insert it
into his anus, is he חייב chayav for משכב זכר? mishkav zachar?
Okay, so which is very bizarre because you know you would assume
that it is an act that requires two people to be defined
as an act of intercourse. But let us see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
So אמר ליה, Amar leh, he said to him, כבסתן, kabastan, which
is sort of like you know you you you know a troublemaker.
or you're distracting me, you're paining me with your silly questions. אמר
רב אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*, מאי דאיבעיא לך *mai d'ibaia lach*? So
you know Rav Ashi says,
well you know, because like what are you even asking? I don't
even understand how this could be a practical question. בקושי לא Lo,
משכחת לה *Bekoshi lo mishkachat la*, you're not going to find it
in the case where the man actually has an erection, then you
won't be able to physically make that happen. כי משכחת לה במשמש
מת *Ki mishkachat la bimshamesh meit*, the only case you'll have it
is in a case where it is he's doing it with a
non-you know, non-erect penis, that's called משמש מת *meshamesh meit*. למאן דאמר
משמש מת בעריות פטור pattur. *Leman d'amar meshamesh meit ba'arayot patur*,
if you say that you know intercourse with a non-erect penis is
exempt, so הכא נמי פטור *hacha nami patur*, so here too you'd
be exempt. למאן דאמר הכא פטור *Leman d'amar hacha patur*, you'd be
exempt, ולמאן דאמר חייב chayav, *u'leman d'amar chayav*, and if you say
that even in that case it's considered an act of intercourse, הכא
נחייב תרתי *hacha nechayev tartei*, so you would be חייב chayav. *chayav*
twice. מחייב השוכב ומחייב הנשכב *Mechayev hashochev u'mechayev hanishkav*, you're חייב *chayav*
because you're both the penetrator and the penetratee. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* sort of says this is, okay, so it is a bizarre
case, but the answer that it just assumes that it's obvious you'd
be חייב *chayav* and חייב *chayav* twice is very, very strange. You
know, you could obviously say that that's not the only case that
that's not defined as an act of intercourse is with you know,
is is only with two parties. It like reminds me of the
joke, you know, that somebody a ראש ישיבה *Rosh Yeshiva* goes in
to visit a ישיבה *Yeshiva* and they're learning קידושין kiddushin, *Kiddushin*. So
he gets up and he asks like, okay, can an androgynous marry
himself? So everybody, all the students are thinking, well, it's one person,
how do you do an act of קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin*? How can
you give, you know, can you do a מעשה *ma'aseh*, you give
the ring to yourself, is that an act or whatever? And then
anyway, they're going back and forth, and then the ראש ישיבה *Rosh
Yeshiva* says, of course not, he's his sister. So anyway, which is
sort of like this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer. The real answer should
be you can't do it because you're not two people. But anyway,
but it gives an answer sort of from a different perspective. So
I find this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* very, very strange from this. Okay,
בעי מיניה רב ששת *Baei minei Rav Sheshet*, and now we move
on. They asked from רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, עובד כוכבים הבא על
הבהמה Oved kochavim haba al habeheimah, מהו *oved kochavim haba al habehemah
mahu*? Now we're getting actually shifting to from the obligation, you know,
the the sort of transgression of the person to the status of
the animal, because the animal that was involved in an act of
bestiality, the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* says that you know, I mean whatever,
the תורה Torah *Torah* says that you should stone it. And the
משנה mishna *Mishnah* says, gives two reasons, sort of explains it. Let's
go back and read the משנה mishna *Mishnah* on דף נ"ח עמוד
א' *daf nun-chet amud aleph*. It says, אם אדם חטא בהמה behema
במה חטאה *im adam chata behemah be-mah chat'ah*? If if a man
sinned, what did the animal sin? אלא לפי שבא לאדם תקלה takala.
על ידה *Ella lephi she-ba l'adam takalah al yadah*, because it caused
the man to stumble, meaning so it was the object of sin.
So that's one explanation why you stone it. And then it says,
לפיכך אמר כתוב תסקל *lephikach amar katuv tisakel*, therefore you stone it
because it was the stumbling block. דבר אחר Davar acher. *davar acher*,
another explanation, שלא תהא עוברת בשוק ויאמרו זו היא שנסקל פלוני על
ידה *shelo te-hei overet bashuk ve-yomru zu hi sheniskal ploni al yadah*,
it shouldn't be passing through the marketplace and people will say, oh,
you know, this is the animal that led so-and-so to be stoned.
So the first thing is considered תקלה takala *takalah*, a you know,
a stumbling block, and the second is a קלון Kalon. *kalon*, embarrassment,
a shaming. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try
to understand which of these two is you know, is more key.
So let's take a look. So let's so let's go back. So
בעי מיניה רב ששת *baei minei Rav Sheshet* asked רב ששת *Rav
Sheshet*, עובד כוכבים הבא על הבהמה *oved kochavim haba al habehemah*, first
wide line in עמוד א' *amud aleph*, if a non-Jew has intercourse
with an animal, מהו *mahu*? What do you do with the animal?
Assuming that, you know, it's under our our our aegis, our jurisdiction,
and you know, we now have to decide, you know, we know
that's חייבי מיתות בית דין *chayavei mitot beit din*, it's a חייב
*chayav* of one of the שבע מצוות בני נח *sheva mitzvot bnei
Noach*. You know, what should we do with the animal? Okay, so
מהו *mahu*? תקלה takala. וקלון בעינן *Takalah ve-kalon ba'inan*? Do
you need both things to be true? Both a stumbling block for
sin and a shaming? והכא ve-hacha, תקלה takala. איכא קלון Kalon, ליכא
*Vehacha takalah ika kalon leika*? And here there's a stumbling block because
it's one of the שבע מצוות בני נח *sheva mitzvot bnei Noach*,
but it's not shaming. Why is it not shameful? So רש"י *Rashi*
has two explanations. One is, well, non-Jews just, it's more the norm
for them, so it's not, it's not you know, in terms of
their you know, societal norms, it's not shameful. All right, that certainly
if you learn גמרא Gemara עבודה זרה avoda zara *Gemara Avodah Zarah*,
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tends to assume by non-Jews. But
the other explanation is less judgmental, basically just says it's not our
responsibility to protect them from being ashamed. Okay, so so that therefore
we should be you know, you know, we should be, we shouldn't
have to do it, do you say that? או דילמא *O dilma*,
or do you say תקלה takala אף על פי שאין קלון Kalon
*takalah af al pi she-ein kalon*, it's enough that it caused a
stumble, that's enough of a reason to stone the animal even if
there's no concern of shaming? Good question. אמר רב ששת תניתוה *Amar
Rav Sheshet tanituah*, we taught it in our משנה mishna *Mishnah*—excuse me,
we taught it in a ברייתא *Baraita*—מה אילנות *mah ilanos*, and this
is going to talk about destroying the trees that the non-Jews were
עובד *oved*... of עבודה זרה. avoda zara, You know, the אשרות. Asherot.
מה אילנות שאין אוכלים ואין שותים, Ma ilanos she'ein ochlim ve'ein shotim,
they don't eat and drink, ואין מריחים, ve'ein merichim, they don't smell,
אמרה תורה השחת שרוף וכלה, amrah Torah hashcheis srof vechale, the Torah
says destroy, burn, and destroy, הלא באו על ידם תקלה, hala ba'u
al yadam takala,
because they cause people to sin and they were the object of
sin, המטה חברו מדרכי חיים לדרכי מיתה על אחת כמה וכמה. hamateh
chavero midarchei chayim ledarchei misa al achas kama vechama.
Somebody who, you know, actively a human being who makes a choice
and actively causes somebody to stray and cause somebody to leave the
path of life to a path of sin, how much more so
are they deserving of destruction. But the point being that why do
you destroy the אשרות Asherot because of תקלה. takala Now that's not
necessarily the point in the Torah. The Torah you destroy them because
having them around can lead to future sin, not because of, or
just עבודה זרה avoda zara, inherently is abominable, not because it necessarily
was just the object of a sin. But nevertheless, that's here how
it is being framed that it's the object of a sin. So
you see that suffices and if that suffices it should suffice in
the case of the non-Jew as well. Okay. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata,
the Gemara says wait, wait, wait. That doesn't exactly work. If that's
really the focus that תקלה takala is enough and even by like
עבודה זרה, avoda zara. עובד כוכבים המשתחווה לבהמתו תיאסר מקטלא? oved kochavim
hamishtachaveh levehemto titasar maktala?
So when a non-Jew bows down to his animal, so, you know,
it should be you should kill have to kill the animal and
should be forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah,
and because again, same way if a non-Jew if you said has
intercourse we would do it because of תקלה. Takala So if a
non-Jew bows down to his animal and you're learning it out from
עבודה זרה, avoda zara we should also do the same because of
תקלה. Takala מי גמידי, Mi gamidi,
but you can't say that דלישראל לא אסור עובד כוכבים אסור? de'Yisrael
lo asur oved kochavim asur? And
but that's not true because in the case of a Jew, so
if a Jew were to bow down to an animal, it would
not become forbidden. Animals do not become forbidden, they do not be
treated as idols and אסור בהנאה asur behana'ah and don't have to
get stoned just because they were worshipped. So it's not true in
a case of a Jew, so how could it be true in
a case of a non-Jew? All right? So we wouldn't say that
if a Jew bows down it's okay but a non-Jew bows down
it's no good. So in general we got a problem here because
the logic
of תקלה Takala? does not apply to other cases of, you know,
it might apply to בהמה behema but it shouldn't apply to cases
of עבודה זרה. avoda zara And then the Gemara says, you know,
it's not only that it would be out of sync between a
Jew and a non-Jew, but this whole idea of אשרה Asherah is
still we're still left with understanding why not why not apply it
to the case of a Jew? If that's really the logic behind
the אשרה. Asherah. So the Gemara says let's take a look. ישראל
גופיה ליסר מדי דהוה ארביע? Yisrael gufei liser midei dehavo arevi'a?
And so you know what? And the Gemara and why not let
the Jew's בהמה beheima. be forbidden because just why just because of
similar to the case of אשרה Asherah or similar to the case
of
bestiality. So the Gemara is saying is wait, wait, wait. You cannot
say that תקלה Takala suffices and we're going to apply the whole
and we learn that from the עבודה זרה avoda zara. category of
אשרה Asherah because clearly there's a problem here with this עבודה זרה
avoda zara category and saying תקלה takalah because it doesn't apply even
to the case of a Jew let alone to the case of
a non-Jew. So obviously there's something out of sync here with trying
to learn it from עבודה זרה. avoda zara, So let's see what
the Gemara says because we know that the case of a Jew
having intercourse with an animal you kill it but not worshipping an
animal you don't kill the animal, so something different is going on
here. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so let's take a look.
זה קלונו מרובה וזה קלונו מועט. Ze klono meruba veze klono mu'at.
So Abaye says yeah, there's a difference. There's a difference between the
case of bowing down to an animal and intercourse with an animal
let's just focus on the case of a Jew. You know, intercourse
is very shameful to do that act. Bowing down is not the
same degree of shame. So therefore we will kill the animal in
case of intercourse because of the issue of shame, but we won't
kill it in the case of being worshipped, let's just focus right
now on the Jew. That explains that difference, okay? Because you have
to now explain why not? Okay, but now how is that different
than the case of the trees? Of the case of the אשרה.
Asherah.
והרי אילנות דאין קלונו מרובה ואמרה תורה השחת שרוף וכלה? Veha'ilanos de'ein
klono meruba ve'amrah Torah hashcheis srof vechale? How about trees? That's not
very shameful, it's not the same as bestiality and the Torah says
destroy. So the Gemara says בבעלי חיים קאמינא. beva'alei chayim ka'aminun. No,
no, no, we're talking about living animals דחס רחמנא עלייהו. dechas Rachmana
aleihu. There the Torah doesn't want is more concerned about living animals
than it is about, you know, trees and therefore only with a
very high threshold. So what has Abaye said? Said don't go give
me examples from destroying the trees, okay, and אשרה Asherah and destroying
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah stuff. First of all I would just say
that's עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah. it's a different reason why you destroy
them. But also it's not living animals so it's not. relevant, you
need a much higher threshold if you're gonna kill an animal. And
when you come to animals, you want to understand what's the difference
between עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. and between, what do you call it,
and between that you don't kill the animal, and bestiality that you
do? The difference is, there's much more shame in the bestiality than
there is in the עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah, That explains all the
evidence. Okay, how would this then apply to the case of the
non-Jew with the animal?
So,
then you would have to actually say you have two options. Abaye's
explained the evidence before you get to the case of the non-Jew
with the animal. But to explain the evidence you need to introduce
the idea of shame, of קלון. Kalon, And that's the difference between
bestiality and עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So then applying to the non-Jew,
you'd say, oh, by the non-Jew, we're not concerned about shame and
you need shame as a relevant factor, so therefore you don't kill
the animal. Or he might say shame is an issue, the shame
of the bestiality is an issue even for a non-Jew. Rashi gives
both possibilities. But bottom line for אביי, Abaye, the explaining the evidence
before you get to the non-Jew is with animals you need a
high threshold, and that high threshold requires high degree of shame. Whether
to apply it to the non-Jew or not is a different question.
That's what אביי Abaye says. רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says, we're
now four lines from the bottom, אמר תורה בהמה נהנית מעבירה תהרג.
Amar Tora beheimah nehenis me'aveirah tehareig.
So Rava says the difference again between the animals and the trees
is, excuse me, between the animal of bestiality and the animal of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, is whether the animal really got pleasure from
it, was considered to be an active part if you want or
just a subject of the act or just an object of the
act. Okay, so in the case of bestiality, the animal is much
more a subject of the act, it got benefit of pleasure, at
least that's what we're asserting, and therefore you kill it, not in
the case of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah, והרי אילנות, Vaharei ilanos,
same point, but by the trees דאין נהנין מעבירה ואמר תורה השחת
שרוף וכלה, De'ein nehenin me'aveirah ve'amar Tora hash-chais sruf vechaleh, but by
the trees didn't get benefit and you still destroy them. Same answer,
בבעלי חיים קאמינא דחס רחמנא עלייהו, Bevahalei chayim kamina dechas rachmana aleiyu,
we're talking about animals that the Torah has compassion. So the same
basic point. Don't bring me any proofs from destroying trees of עבודה
זרה, those are not living animals, that's a completely different threshold. When
you come to living animals, you have to have a much higher
threshold before you kill it. What is that higher threshold? For Abaye,
it is shame, and for Rava, it is the animal got pleasure.
That does not apply to עבודה זרה, would apply to a non-Jew.
So for Rava presumably the answer is obviously yes, there's תקלה takalah
and there's the animal had pleasure. For אביי Abaye it is debatable.
Okay. So now the Gemara continues. תא שמע. Ta shema. We haven't
answered our question though, what is the story about a non-Jew? Come
and hear. דבר אחר. davar acher Now we're going to look at
our Mishnah. שלא תהא בהמה עוברת בשוק ויאמרו זו היא הנסקלה פלוני
על ידה. Shelo tehei beheimah overes bashuk veyomru zo hi sheniskala ploni
al yadah. It shouldn't be going in the marketplace and people say,
ah, this is the animal that caused so-and-so to get stoned. And
the Gemara is going to assume that that contains that last דבר
אחר davar acher two elements: a קלון, kalon the embarrassment, passing in
the marketplace, public shaming. But because it mentions that he was נסקל
על ידה, niskal al yadah, it didn't say that this person did
this disgusting act. It said that he was נסקל על ידה. niskal
al yadah. There's also the idea of תקלה takalah, also is indicated
in that second explanation. So מאי לאו? Mai lav? Is it not
the case? Top of נה עמוד ב. Nun-He Amud Bet. Is it
not the case, מדסיפא תקלה וקלון, mide'seifa Takala ve'Kalon, the second דבר
אחר davar acher, of the Mishnah of the animal passing in the
marketplace refers to both the stumbling and the shaming. רישא תקלה בלא
קלון. Reisha Takala belo Kalon. When the first part says because it
was בא תקלה על ידו ba Takala al yado by just saying
that by itself, and then it said דבר אחר, davar acher, means
that stumbling is sufficient for the reason to stone it. And if
that is true, then that would therefore apply even to the case
of the non-Jew and the animal. והיכי דמי? Veheichi dami? What's the
case of just תקלה? takalah עובד כוכבים הבא על הבהמה,
the case of the non-Jew. Okay, so even if קלון k'lon is
not a necessary piece of the equation. All right, so don't you
see that?
לא, Lo. says the Gemara, no. סיפא תקלה וקלון, Seifa Takala ve'Kalon,
it's true the second case indicates both the תקלה takalah, and the
קלון, k'lon. both of those. רישא, Reisha, the first case, שבאת תקלה
על ידו, shebas Takala al yado, הכא קא משמע לן דאפילו קלון
בלא תקלה. hacha ka mashma lan de'afilu Kalon belo Takala. Very bizarrely,
the Gemara is saying that the first line of the Mishnah that
says why do you stone it because a stumbling came, says maybe
we should read that not as a stumbling of sin, but a
stumbling of shaming. So the second case that mentions סקילה Skilah indicates
that it caused you to sin and also shame, marketplace. The first
case of stumbling maybe just means a stumbling of shaming. Okay, so
how could that be? דאפילו קלון בלא תקלה. De'afilu Kalon belo Takala.
What's an example of shaming without stumbling? without sin, without stumbling, נמי
מחייב, Nami mechayev, היכי דמי? Heichi dami?
What's the case? ישראל הבא על בהמה בשוגג, Yisrael haba al behema
beshogeg, like a Jew did it, but without realizing that it was
אסור. Assur. Now, I don't know sin, it's a sin בשוגג, beshogeg,
but it's not the same degree of sin. So you don't have
the תקלה takalah, of being חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but it still
is a shameful thing to be engaging in. Maybe you could also
ask the case of let's say it was a קטן katan or
something. Okay, so maybe that's the case of the משנה. mishnah. וכדבעי
רב
המנונא, Uchidba'ei Rav Hamnuna, like רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna asks, דבעי רב
המנונא, Deba'ei Rav Hamnuna, ישראל הבא על בהמה בשוגג מהו? Yisrael haba
al behema beshogeg mahu? Okay, so these are like the flip side
of the coins. The non-Jew with the animal is seen to be
a case of תקלה takalah. without shame, and the Jew doing it
בשוגג beshogeg is seen to be as a case of shame without
תקלה, takalah. without sin. Okay, הבא על בהמה בשוגג מהו? Haba al
behema beshogeg mahu? תקלה וקלון בעינא? Takalah vekalon ba'ina? Do you need
both? והכא קלון איכא תקלה ליכא. Vehacha kalon ika takalah leika. And
in this case, you only have the shame and not the sin.
או דילמא קלון אף על פי שאין תקלה? O dilma kalon af
al pi she'ein takalah? Or do you say shame suffices and therefore
even though you only have the shame, that would be enough? Okay,
so those are the two cases that we want to know. What
if you only have one and not the other? And we're reading
the second case in the משנה mishnah, about the passing in the
marketplace to indicate both factors, and then the question is how do
you read the first case of the משנה mishnah to indicate just
תקלה takala is enough? That's a simple reading, and then it would
say the case of a non-Jew חייב, the case of שוגג shogeg
פטור. Or do you read it to say just קלון k'lon is
enough, and then it would be the reverse. Okay, so let's take
a look. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, says רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. בת שלוש שנים ויום
אחד מתקדשת בביאה. Bas shalosh shanim veyom echad miskadeshes beviah.
This is a famous,
you
know, משנה mishnah. in נדה Niddah which lays out, quoted in multiple
places,
the different ages that are relevant for boys and girls in הלכה
halacha status. And as I mentioned, three years and a day for
a girl, nine years and a day for a boy is very
relevant for determining the act of intercourse. Okay, and we'll eventually see
how this is relevant for us, but first let's understand what this
is talking about. So if you have a girl that's three years
and a day, מתקדשת בביאה, miskadeshes beviah, her,
if an adult has intercourse with her—again, it's child abuse and horrific
and so on, but okay, halachically it's considered an act of intercourse.
So if her father married her off to a man—now her father
can marry her off to a man even if she's less than
three years and a day and just accept like a קידושין, kiddushin
money for קידושין kiddushin for her, you know, any as long as
she's under twelve, no matter how young she is. But if rather
than accepting money for קידושין kiddushin for her, he says he gives
her to this man and says have intercourse with her and that'll
be the act of קידושין—and this is totally horrific, but that's what
we're talking about, okay—then once she's three years and a day, the
act of intercourse is defined as an act of intercourse and she
is halachically married to this man. ואם בא עליה יבם קנאה. Ve'im
ba aleha yabam keno'ah. And if she she had been married by
her father and then her husband died, and now she's three years
and a day and the husband's brother, there were no kids, she's
only three years and a day, the husband's brother does an act
of יבום, yibum, that act of יבום, yibum, meaning having intercourse with
her, makes her his wife, but that would only be if she
is three years and a day. Younger than that, it would not
be defined as an act of intercourse and he would still have
to either do חליצה chalitzah or wait till she was older and
then do the act of intercourse. וחייבין עליה משום אשת איש. Vechayavin
aleha mishum eshes ish. Okay,
and if somebody has intercourse with her and she is three years
and a day and has been married off by the father, תוספות
Tosafos says even if married off just through this act of ביאה,
bi'ah, or married to the יבם yabam through this act of ביאה,
bi'ah, anyway that act of ביאה bi'ah makes her fully married, and
similarly if a man now has intercourse with her and she's only
three years and a day, that is a full prohibitive act of
intercourse and he will have committed adultery and be חייב. ומטמא את
בועלה לטמא משכב תחתון כעליון. Umetama es bo'ala letame mishkav tachton ke'elyon.
The תורה Torah says that if a man has intercourse with a
נדה, Niddah, then he has the same טומאה tumah that the נדה
Niddah has. Okay, the and he as opposed to if he just
touches a נדה, Niddah, then she is an אב av and he
would be a ראשון, rishon, a first-degree derivative. If he has intercourse
with a נדה, Niddah, he is also an אב, av, he is
also the primary source of טומאה. tumah. Now, the one difference between
him and the נדה Niddah is the principle of משכב. mishkav. משכב,
mishkav, the תורה Torah, says if a woman, if a נדה Niddah
is sitting or a זב zav or זבה zavah is sitting on
a seat or on a cushion, even not directly touching it, even
like there're ten cushions stacked up, all the cushions she is sitting
on, they all are considered the משכב, mishkav, the sitting place of
a נדה, Niddah, and they all are an אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
They all considered a primary טומאה, tumah, not one degree removed. That's
the principle of משכב. mishkav. The same is true by the בועל
נדה, bo'el niddah, the man who had intercourse with a נדה. Niddah.
He is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Anything he sits on however,
even if it's ten degrees, like ten cushions or twenty, whatever, you
know, even if he's not touching it, has the status of a
משכב, mishkav, but because he is not a נדה Niddah himself, it
only becomes a ראשון. rishon. So, it has the- the משכב mishkav
idea is he doesn't have to directly touch it, even if there's
stacked pillows, every single pillow under him has that status, but it
is not an אב, av, it's a ראשון. rishon. And that's what
it means ומטמא את בועלה, u-metamei es bo'alah, so she makes the
man who has intercourse with her, this three-year-old girl, three years and
one day, who has her period,
that he becomes טמא tamei like she is, an אב, av, לטמא
משכב תחתון כעליון, le-tamei mishkav tachton ke-elyon, and would make the bottom,
you know, sort of
cushion טמא tamei just like the top cushion, but it really means
only with one degree removed, only as a ראשון. rishon. ניסת, Niset,
now. ניסת לכהן, Niset le-kohen, if this three-year-old and one-day girl gets
married to a כהן, kohen, אוכלת בתרומה. ochelet be-trumah. She can eat
תרומה. trumah. The principle is that from the תורה, Torah a woman
married to a כהן kohen can eat תרומה trumah even if there's-
it's just קידושין and not נישואין. nisuin. But דרבנן, de-rabbanan, she only
eats תרומה trumah once there's actually been נישואין nisuin to the כהן,
kohen, so because she only when she is fit to be able
to have what, you know, it's considered to be an act of
intercourse were they to have it, only then when they're living together
is it considered נישואין. nisuin. The idea of נישואין nisuin of living
together means in a context where they could be having sex. So
since when she's three and a day they're considered to have actually
had נישואין, nisuin, then she can eat תרומה trumah if her husband
is a כהן. kohen. בא עליה אחד מן הפסולים, Ba aleha echad
min ha-psulim, פסלה מן הכהונה. pasla min ha-kehunah.
If somebody who is invalid like a ממזר, mamzer, for example, has
intercourse with her, or a חלל, chalal, or whatever, then again, when
a woman has intercourse with somebody who is, you know, let's say
a בת כהן bat kohen has intercourse with somebody that is פסול,
pasul, that makes her a חללה chalalah and now she cannot marry
a כהן, kohen, okay? So, פסולים פסלה מן הכהונה. psulim pasla min
ha-kehunah.
And the same would be true also if she was not a
בת כהן, bat kohen, if she was just a ישראלית yisraelit or
לוויה, leviah, you know, also, this act of intercourse with somebody פסול
pasul would make her invalid for a כהן. kohen. Okay, but again,
that's only considered an act of intercourse once she is three years
and- three years and one day. ואם בא עליה אחד מכל העריות
האמורות בתורה, Ve-im ba aleha echad mi-kol ha-arayot ha-amurot ba-torah, מומתין על
ידה, mumatin al yadah, והיא פטורה. ve-hi peturah. And if any case
of any of the forbidden acts of sex, you know, case of
like whatever, any of the incestuous relationships and so on, were to
have intercourse with her, because it's an act of intercourse, the man
is put to death, he's an adult. She is exempt, she is
a minor, but it is considered an act of intercourse once she
is three years and a day. Okay, so that's the basic principle,
all the ramifications of once she's three years and a day, it's
considered to be an act of intercourse. Now, והיא פטורה. ve-hi peturah.
Now, what does any of this have to do with us? Let's
take a look. אחת מכל העריות, Achat mi-kol ha-arayot, any of the
עריות, arayot, ואפילו בהמה, ve-afilu behemah, presumably even an animal that had
intercourse with her. She would be exempt and the animal would be
stoned. Okay,
והכא, v'hacha, דקלון איכא, de-kalon ika, there's shame, you know, it's a
shameful thing to do, presumably even for a
minor. תקלה ליכא, Takalah leka, but it is not a sin, she's
a minor. So therefore you see that that suffices, shame alone suffices.
וקתני מומתין על ידה. Ve-katani mumatin al yadah. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, כיון דמזידה היא תקלה נמי איכא, kevan de-mezidah hi takalah
nami ika, ורחמנא הוא דחס עלה. ve-rachmana hu de-chas alah. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, there's a difference between being willful and a
minor, and being a שוגג, shogeg, being unin- not even aware that
it's a sin. Okay, if you are- if she's willfully engaging in
this, again, how willful is a three-year-old? But okay, so then it
is considered that she sinned, but she's exempt from punishment, but it
is a תקלה, takala it did cause her to sin. It's just
she gets a waiver from being punished. ורחמנא הוא דחס עלה, Ve-rachmana
hu de-chas alah, the תורה Torah, had compassion. עלה דידה חס, Alah
didah chas, on her it had compassion, אבהמה לא חס, a-behemah lo
chas, not on the animal. But it could still be an issue
of תקלה, takala. right? This person willfully sinned with this animal, and
it caused this person to sin, the person won't be punished, she's
a minor, but the animal will be stoned because it caused her
to sin. So it's very interesting that the גמרא is saying that
when you compare these two cases, a minor, literally if a three-year-old,
whatever, you know, willfully quote-unquote doing this act is considered more a
sin that you're exempt from, but it was a sin, so we're
going to kill the animal, as opposed to a case of שוגג,
shogeg, not knowing that it's forbidden, where actually that is considered not
actually the same way a sin. Now of course a שוגג shogeg
is a sin, it's why you bring a קרבן, korban, okay, but
it's not the same degree of a תקלה. takala That is interesting,
I would have more naturally have said the opposite, but okay, willful
sin that caused, you know, somebody to sin במזיד, be-mezid, kill the
animal. In the other case, it was an adult but it wasn't
במזיד, be-mezid, don't kill the animal, that's not considered the same degree
of תקלה. takala. So we cannot prove it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
תא שמע. ta shema. So we're going to try again, and this
case, from the definition of intercourse by the boy. One wonders also
if the גמרא is partly bringing this because since we're talking about
these sexual sins, it's a good opportunity to define what is the
age of intercourse for a girl and for a boy. Okay, it's
not just for this question about when do you kill the animal.
Anyway, רבא Rava says, come and hear. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד
הבא על יבמתו קנאה. Ben tesha shanim v'yom echad haba al yivimto
kna'ah. If a nine year old boy and one day, then it's
considered an act of intercourse if he has it with a, you
know, adult female. So, so if he's nine years and one day
and he has intercourse with a his sister-in-law, his brother's, his dead
brother's wife, then that is an act of יבום. yibum. Okay now
actually that's only דרבנן, drabbanan, דאורייתא d'oraisa not, but that's but whatever,
we're just going to bracket that. Fundamentally it's an act of intercourse.
ואינו נותן גט עד שיגדיל. V'eino nosein get ad sheyagdil. But if
now he wants to divorce his sister-in-law, now that they're halachically married,
he has to wait until he becomes an adult because the giving
of a גט get requires being an adult. ומטמא כנידה לטמא משכב
תחתון כעליון. Um'tamei k'niddah l'tamei mishkav tachton k'elyon.
And if he now this nine year and one day has intercourse
with a woman who's a נידה, niddah, then again, he is a
בועל נידה bo'el niddah because now it's an act of intercourse, he's
nine years and a day, and he has he becomes an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, and the things that he sits on are also
even ten even ten pillows even the bottom one are also considered
a משכב, mishkav, although they would be a ראשון. rishon. פוסל ואינו
מאכיל. Posel v'eino ma'achil.
If she is פסול, pasul, if he's like a ממזר mamzer or
whatever and he has sex with a woman, he and makes her
now because it's an act of intercourse, he makes her invalid to
marry a כהן, kohen, but if he is a כהן kohen and
married to a woman, because he cannot have sex, right, it's not
halachically defined as intercourse, then she cannot eat תרומה, terumah, they're not
considered to have נישואין. nisuin. ופוסל את הבהמה מעל גבי המזבח. Uposel
es habeheima mei'al gabi hamizbeiach. If he has intercourse with an animal,
it cannot be used as a קרבן. korban. An animal that's been
engaged in bestiality cannot be used as a קרבן. korban. Now you'll
say what do you mean, anyway you should be stoning it. Okay,
but if they're not עדים eidim that we can stone it, but
the owner or but there's an עד אחד eid echad or the
owner admits that it was part of an act of bestiality, then
even though you don't stone it, it cannot be used as a
קרבן. korban. So when is it considered this act? When he is
nine years and one day. ונסקלת על ידו. V'nisqueles al yado. And
the animal will be stoned. Here it's explicit. Before it was implied
by the case of the girl, but here it's explicit, the case
of bestiality, that a nine year old and a day has intercourse
with an animal, the animal is stoned. ואם בא על אחת מכל
עריות שבתורה מומתות על ידו. V'im ba al achas mikol arayos shebatorah
mumasos al yado. And if he has intercourse with any of the
forbidden sexual you know women in the תורה, Torah then they are
adults, they would be put to death if they did it במזיד,
b'mezid, he would be exempt, again nine years and a day is
an act of intercourse. But we're saying all of this because of
the case of בהמה. behemah. Okay
והכא, in this case, קלון איכא תקלה ליכא. k'lon ika takala leika.
Same assumption we had before. It's shameful for him to engage in
this act, but it wasn't a stumbling, he's a minor. Okay so
therefore, and nevertheless you're going to stone the animal. So you see
that shame is enough. So the גמרא says וקתני נסקלת על ידו
v'kasni nisqueles al yado and you stone it. No. So the גמרא
says no, כיון דמזיד הוא תקלה נמי איכא. keivan d'mezid hu takala
nami ika. No, even though he's exempt from punishment, he did it
willfully, and therefore it is considered to be a stumbling. Okay, ורחמנא
הוא דחסי עליה. v'rachmana hu dechasi aleih. The תורה just said look
you willfully sinned, you did a sin, but you're a minor, you
won't get punished, we'll go easy on you. Okay עליה דידיה חס,
aleih dideih chas, on him he had compassion, ורחמנא אבהמה לא חס,
v'rachmana abeheima lo chas, but not on the animal. You did a
willful sinning sinning act with this animal, the animal caused you to
sin, we're going to stone it. So again the גמרא is saying
we're willing to assume that a case of a minor, again even
the case of the girl even three year old, engaging in a
willful act, but even though they're a minor is considered more case
of תקלה takala, than an adult engaging in it בשוגג. bishogeg. And
therefore maybe the reason you stone is still the תקלה takala reason
and maybe it is not the קלון k'lon reason. Okay. תא שמע.
Ta shema. One last try going back to our משנה. Mishnah דבר
אחר שלא תהא בהמה עוברת בשוק ויאמרו זו היא שנסקל פלוני על
ידה.
Davar acher shelo tehei beheima overes bashuk v'yomru zu hi shenisqal ploni
al
yadah. The second case of the משנה, it shouldn't be passing in
a marketplace, this is what caused so-and-so to get stoned, which we
assume refers to both the case of shame and תקלה.
מאי לאו. Mai lav. So now the גמרא's just doing the mirror
image of what it did before in the case of the case
of the נכרי. nochri. The נכרי nochri and the animal was the
case of תקלה without קלון. The Jew of in the בשוגג bishogeg
was a case of קלון without תקלה. So מאי לאו, mai lav,
is it not the
case, מדסיפא תקלה וקלון, mideiseifa takala v'k'lon, the end case is both
stumbling and shame, רישא reisha קלון בלא belo תקלה, the first case
of "this caused תקלה" means the stumbling of shaming? Again very strange
read of the first case. But the first case of the משנה
זו שבאת תקלה על ידה zu sheba'as takala al yadah means this
caused shame. So don't you see that shame suffices, that's the point
of the first case? Or the first reason in the משנה. והיכי
דמי ישראל הבא על בהמה בשוגג. V'heichi dami Yisrael haba al beheima
bishogeg. And we're talking about a case of שוגג. shogeg. לא. No.
We could go back and say it means what it... what we
said before. סיפא תקלה וקלון, saifa takalah v’kalon, the second case is
both shame and stumbling, stumbling and shame, excuse me. רישא תקלה בלא
קלון. reisha takalah b’lo kalon. The first case maybe is just stumbling
without shame, which is what it sounds like. והיכי דמי עובד כוכבים
הבא על הבהמה, v’heichi dami oved kochavim haba al habehemah, that would
be the first scenario we were talking about, a non-Jew with an
animal, וכדבעי מיניה רב ששת, u’chedebei minei Rav Sheshet, like the question
of Rav Sheshet. So from our משנה and the דבר אחר, we
understand that one of the reasons should suffice by the case of
בהמה. Either stumbling or shame, and we just don’t know which one
suffices, and the question would be the case of the non-Jew with
the animal is considered to be a case of stumbling without shame,
and the Jew בשוגג b’shogeg is considered to be a case of
shame without stumbling, and we don’t know which of the two reasons
suffices by itself. We will end here.